The first data type we will cover is the string
data type.
Strings of text go inside quotation marks
and are very versatile in how they are used
in the context of a program.
In this first code example, a file called
111-str, we see two variables with strings:
one containing a first name and one containing
a last name.
Before getting more into strings, let’s
go through a basic programming tenet: variables.
A variable is a container that stores a value,
like a string of text, a number, or other
data types.
I have two such variables on lines 1 and 2,
first_name and last_name.
Variable names can contain letters, numbers,
and underscores but not symbols.
They cannot contain spaces.
If you have any experience with C# or Java
or JavaScript, you may have seen variables
using camel case, which makes the first word
lowercase, and all subsequent words start
with a capital letter.
You can use camel casing in Python, but the
standard naming convention in Python is to
use all lowercase characters with underscores
replacing spaces.
I want to output this as a full name, so on
line 3, I will type print(last_name +”,
“ + first_name) with a space before the
comma.
A print statement creates output.
Within that print statement, any literal text,
like the comma and space we see here, must
be inside quotation marks.
Let’s run this code in a terminal to ensure
it works.
I will select the Run Python File icon, and
below, on the Terminal tab, we will see the
results: my last name, comma, and first name.
Though not on the exam, one question when
learning a programming language is: do we
use single quotes around text strings or double
quotes?
Double quotes work.
But what if I change the quotes inside the
print statement to single quotes?
I will rerun this code, and it works.
This output speaks to Python's versatility,
where we can use single or double quotes but
not curly quotes, as is often the case with
quotes pasted from Word, so be aware of that
possible issue.
You may be wondering when the quotes used
matter, then.
Let me show you an example of when it does
matter.
I will skip a line and add this print statement
to line 5: print (‘Jason’s turn’) and
then attempt to run this code.
Notice that we get an error message.
Why?
Because Python thinks we have an opening quote
here with no closing quote, which will generate
an error message.
But, if I change the quotes here to double
quotes, this runs again because, now, the
single quote is ignoring these double quotes.